ok
Jaden, can you see everything?
I can see the board.
Hang on, any writing?
I'm writing on the board.
Yeah, I can see that too.
All right, cool.
We got everything.
Thank you.
All right.
Well, we have a small room tonight, three people.
You're welcome to move up closer.
I don't bite.
you want to stay back there that's ok too, whatever you want to do. Usually we have people
filled in. So a couple announcements, there's still one of you who I just emailed who hasn't
registered for the midterm, who needs to. Those of you who are in Section 901 don't need to register,
so if you've got emails from me saying to register for the midterm you need to do that,
as required, so please do that immediately.
And the midterm will be next week.
Those of you who are in the Flex Section, 941,
you can actually start taking it tomorrow,
and you have until the end of the day,
Tuesday, 9 p.m. next week.
So please register and that will be good for me so that I don't have to worry about you.
Yeah?
I just want to double check about the registration thing.
Yeah.
So if I'm an 8% student, do I still have to like?
So if you look in, actually I'll show you.
if you look in D2L for the class, I think down here there's like I don't know if you see the
CDM proctor exams. So if you're in 941 you should see a way to click over. If you're in 901 like
the non-flex section then you should even if there might be something here that will just take you
in but you won't see this class pop up. So just check what section you're registered in. If you're
you're 901 then you just come here. I have to say this because I have
students who are 941 and the 941 people need to register because we have limited
seating in here so that way I it's like first-come-first-serve right like if
you register you get a seat in the room and if you don't register then you don't
have anywhere to go take the exam which is why I ask you to register because
there's a whole proctoring office that handles things. So that's why I do that.
Thanks for a double check. Yeah, sure. No problem.
So then in two weeks, so we are at week
five. So we'll have the exam next week. Before I say the two
week thing, we'll have the exam next week and then the second half of class we're going to cover some
additional material. So that'll be new material. Also, just so you know, the
material we cover tonight will not be on the midterm. So the
The midterm only covers up to week four, formal semantics,
which we did last week.
So midterm is just weeks one through four.
New stuff tonight is not included.
And then next week, we will have lecture for the second half.
And then what I started to say, and I
will send email out about this.
The week of May 12, I will be traveling on business.
So I will be in my hotel room teaching class from there.
Luckily, last quarter, I have a pen display,
so I can whiteboard, which is great.
I had surgery last December,
so I was not able to lift my arm and pull right out of the board.
So I bought a thing, so bringing that with me
so I can do any white boarding we need to do.
So we'll have class on Zoom for everybody.
I will send the Zoom link out for that.
That will be recorded.
So normally if anybody's watching this on Course Online, normally you watch their, I don't record the Zoom meeting.
But next week, and Jayden, please make sure next week that I remember to press record in Zoom.
I'm just calling that out for our online learning ambassador to make sure that I get that.
Because those of you who either want to view the lecture after class or the students who are not attending live,
we'll watch the Zoom recording.
So all of that will be communicated clearly.
The Wednesday office hours, I'm going to need to move.
I need to figure out what I want to do with that.
That's next week, not this week.
The reason for that, sorry, that's not next week.
That's two weeks.
That's not this week or next week.
That's the week I'm in business
because I'll be having business dinners
and things like that on Wednesday nights.
So I will figure out what the schedule looks like
for this week, probably by the end of this week.
and get that communicated to you. So far nobody's coming to office hours.
Usually after the exam everybody wants to come to office hours. It's like I get
like suddenly everybody wants to know what happened. My suggestion is if you
usually come to the classroom I do office hours before class so my
suggestion would be if you want to see, we can talk in generalities,
but if you if you normally come here I won't have all the exams with me when I
travel. So it's probably best for you to... if you want to see what you did, either
come to the classroom from office hours and let me know. I will announce all this
at the time. Let me know so I can pull your exam and bring it with me, because I
don't always bring them all to the classroom. If you're fully remote or
you're like in another city and you don't come downtown to the class, we can
can do that. I can show you your exam during office hours. I will have the electronic versions
on here, but I won't have the answer sheets because I have your answer sheets, but I...
No, I take that back. If you're remote and you take the exam remote, I will have it all on my
computer. So just ping me and let me know what you want to do after you get the exam score.
So the exam will be Tuesday. I will have probably the grades by Wednesday, May 6th,
So the grades will be pretty quick.
They're multiple choice, the exam is multiple choice.
So it's easy for me to grade.
So you should be able to let me know
if you wanna see it pretty quick.
Okay, any questions about the exam?
We're gonna do some review tonight as well.
So any questions just about logistics
for the next few weeks?
Anybody online?
Okay, great.
So why don't we get started with the quiz?
We'll just do a little warm up with a quiz we had last week.
So here's our first question.
So we have a Scala function definition here.
What does this function do?
How would we talk about this in English?
How would we describe this?
Anybody want to guess?
Or not guess, but hopefully we can read it and make sense of it.
I'll talk you through it if we have to.
So we have a list, right?
You're doing pattern matching, and you see there's some recursion.
function is f. What's this function doing?
What it's doing is recreating a list until you reach the end of the initial list which is access.
That's part of it. So you're on the right track. What else does it do?
It's taking an element and copying it twice and creating a new.
Yeah, so every place in the original list where an element occurs,
it's creating two elements of that element.
So that's the additional piece, right?
So what you said was correct, but it was only partially correct,
because I always say we're deconstructing this list here.
And then we're constructing a new list, and
you notice the return type of this thing is list of x.
By the way, in Scala, when you do something recursive,
you have to tell it what the return type is.
because the compiler will complain at you and say,
I can't figure this out.
I don't know what you mean.
I need to be sure that you really need this.
So if this is a list, and this y is being cons to the list,
then you're consing it again.
So the question asks, if this function
is executed on a list of length n,
what is the length of the resulting list?
So we just talked about in English what it does.
This is what I'm trying to encourage you to do is look at code and
be able to tell yourself like what does this code do.
So what is the length if we start with a list of length n,
what is the length of the resulting list?
Two n.
Very good, two n.
Does everybody see that?
I hope so.
Basically if every element is being duplicated in line,
then you're just doubling the number of elements in the list.
OK, here's another one.
So here we have a function.
It takes two lists and it's containing it's the lists are containing type X.
And it's returning a list of type X. And we see it is we're abstracting over this type.
That's what this X here means.
And let's let's reason about what does this do?
So pattern matching again, whenever you see pattern matching,
you should look for a base case, which we see and
we see there's a recursive call.
So we're doing something recursively.
Right, so we're gonna get a list and
then we're going to do something with the head of the first list that we got here.
So we are calling this thing,
what would we describe this kind of abstractly?
What does it do?
Just appending the second list to the first list.
Right, so you want to tell us why you, I agree with you.
You want to tell us what led you to see that?
So the second case, it is iterating the first list one by one.
And when we reach the base case, we are finally just appending the second,
this, so I mean, when it gets to the null part,
we are just taking on the second list, and it goes to the second case again and
so on and so forth, it creates a list.
So the language I would choose is slightly different.
So what I would say is we're deconstructing the first list, right?
And when we get to the end of the first list, when we've exhausted all the elements,
we're returning the second list.
And notice we're always passing that second list
without changing it at all, right?
There's no pattern matching on the second list.
We just take whatever we got for YS
and we pass it on down to the next recursive call, right?
So we're deconstructing that first list
and we continually do that as we call recursively.
When we get to the end of it,
we just send back the second list
and notice what we're doing
is we're just consing each element
of that first list back on as we go.
So appending is a good way to describe that, it's a more abstract way to express that.
Okay, now that we've done that, if this function is executed on two lists of length m and n respectively,
so that means of course that this one is length m and this one has length n,
what is the length of the resulting list?
m plus n, very good.
So the reason I'm doing it this way is I'm trying to encourage you to think about describing to yourself what does this function do?
And then a question like this becomes hopefully very easy because you've now kind of created this narrative for yourself like what this function is.
Okay, question three.
So we have another function.
Yeah, we get a list, we return a list.
And if we look at what's happening here,
how would we describe the behavior of this function?
It's reversing the list.
It's reversing the list, okay, tell us why you said that.
So, like, each time we get a element from the list,
we are creating it, and pushing it on the,
let's say at the end, and at the end,
and each time we are calling the function again.
So as we say,
recursively go back,
we are essentially reversing the list.
Yeah, so to express it slightly more succinctly,
what I would say is,
we're deconstructing the list we got,
we're always taking the head of the list
And creating a single element list with it and that's happening here,
it's going here.
But that's happening after we recursively operate on the remainder of the list, right.
So we're going to go all the way down to the end of the list, return nil, and
then we're going to append, that's what this three colons is.
We're going to append a single element list that contains this y.
And as we recurs on up, we'll continue to stick whatever the head was for that sublist on the end through the appending of a single element list.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
So now that we said that, given this list here, my list, we have a list of two tuples.
Yes, two tuples.
This is a two tuple.
And the left element is an int and the right error.
The first element is and in the right.
The second element, there's not really left and right.
That's positional.
So we have a tuple of two ints, and we start off with 12 in a tuple.
34 in a tuple, 56 in a tuple.
So we call f on using my list and we get back what?
All right.
So, Kishan is telling us it's this one.
Why is it not this one?
Well, it's reversing the initial placement of the variables,
five and six are reversed, which it doesn't touch the,
because it's a tuple, it keeps everything together.
So it's not going to touch the individual elements
as if inside of it.
Yeah, very good.
So it's not doing anything to deconstruct the tuple
and reconstruct the tuple with a different
order or anything like that.
So it isn't this one, because we're only reversing the element.
What constitutes an element is the tuple with the five and six
in that position without changing that.
If we were, we could write some code
that would do something different, but we're not doing it.
Actually, one hint for this is we don't ever
deal with tuples here.
We deal with some abstract type x,
so we have no visibility into the fact
that this is a tuple here.
So we couldn't reverse the order.
There's no way to know that it was a tuple inside that code.
And then likewise, this other one is kind of like just
reversing the elements of the tuple,
but leaving the elements of the list in the order that they were.
So this one can't be it either, because, again,
it's not doing anything with the tuple inside.
So cool.
That's good.
All right.
Now we have this Scala code.
We have a list.
Our elements are 1-10.
Then we're calling filter on that list.
So what are we filtering out?
Or what are we filtering in?
Good. Ask it either way.
I often use at work,
I use filter not which is the opposite.
But filter. What are we filtering like?
What are we keeping?
Keeping even the moves.
Even numbers. So that will eliminate 1,
So we'll keep two, four, six, eight, 10.
And that's what's left and now we're going to call map.
When we call map, we take each element and do what?
Line by two.
So which one is the correct answer?
Second.
The second one.
Right, so when we were left with two, four, six, eight, 10, and then we doubled those,
we can just see that that's four, eight, twelve, six, and twenty.
So this time, we're reversing the order of what we're doing.
So first, in the previous question, we were filtering first and keeping the even numbers,
and then we were doubling.
Now we're going to double and then keep the even numbers.
So what's the result there?
The last one.
So when we double these, both the odd and even elements get mapped to even elements all
the time.
So this is how I, when I look at code like this, this is how I reason about it.
Okay, this one is long, so I'm going to make it a little smaller.
I hope it's not too small.
Okay, can everybody see that?
I hope so.
Tell me if you can.
Alright, which type should replace question one and question two?
So this is like, we use this on our exam questions, just sort of mean,
we wanna know, tell me about the types that you can infer what you're seeing.
So we have a function that takes xss of some unknown type.
Notice we have this abstracted type x here, and
then it's gonna refer some other unknown types.
So then we have this thing where we're deconstructing xss.
And then we're also deconstructing x,
and then we're just yielding x.
What does this kind of suggest that we're doing?
We're flattening the list.
Flattening.
Tell us why you said that.
We are doing a double for comprehension.
I put it like that.
So first we are iterating the list inside the list.
and then we are iterating the list as well.
So that's why .
So right there we said we have,
we think we have a list of lists.
Also another clue, although you can't,
this doesn't prove it, but another clue is that
this convention here XSS is usually used
for when you have a list of lists, right.
So this looks like it's probably a list of lists
and then that makes this type what?
this excess is a list of X.
So this is to be clear, list of list of X for $1.
This is a list of X.
And then if I have a list of X,
then X becomes just plain old X.
And because it's a four yield,
I'm doing ultimately a flat map map.
So this is like XSS.flatmap.
And then this is, I can actually draw that.
Just write it on board.
So it looks like,
This is just the body of this function.
This is also the identity function.
Remember that the body of what you pass to map or flat map is also a function.
This is just saying I'm taking each element and binding into x and returning itself.
So when I do a flat map and then internally a map on these types,
and actually what I can do also is make these list of x.
X.
That makes it clear.
So I'm, oh, I need the error.
I'm just saying that xs has this type, and xs has this type.
So, this is another way to write that.
Scala compiler will take that and turn it into this.
It compiles to the same class, java.
All right.
So $1 is looking like a list of a list of x,
and $2 is looking like a list of x, that's what we're returning.
So I think our answer is here.
Everybody see that?
And here's our last one, another one of these.
So here, it looks like we have an f and g,
but we don't have f really defined.
Oh, f is defined, I'm sorry.
f is defined right here.
It's one of the arguments,
one of the parameters to the function.
So that's gonna have,
that $2 is gonna have an arrow in it.
So far I see lots of arrows so we can't just keep it.
Oh, okay, that eliminates this one here, right,
because there's no function involved.
This one does have a function
so we're not really getting very far.
Okay, so let's keep going.
What else do we got?
So this is a function.
And then G, oh I see we're deconstructing something.
We have xs is probably a list of something, right?
Because we're deconstructing.
We see nil so that's our clue, right?
That's our base case.
Nil, that's a list of whatever is contained within xs.
My suggestion to you is that the convention is probably that it's an x.
So I'm going to start with that assumption but
we'll validate that. So we're deconstructing this list. It looks like a list of X and we're
calling f of Y. So if that were a list of X and that would make Ys a list of X, right?
And Y would be X. So that would make F be a function that takes an X and produces something
So alright, we can start to look at these and say, well, this is a list of functions.
Kind of useless, right?
This next one is a list of y.
We already eliminated that.
This one is a function that takes the list of x and produces a list of y.
This one is an x that produces a list of y.
So I think we can say that this is not the one because we're deconstructing a list of
something, I guess $1 could be a list of list of x. But let's let's stay with our
assumption here. It looks to me like it's an x. And then notice the operator
here is a double colon, right? So we're conzing, we're not appending, right? If we
were appending, this would have to be a list, right? Everybody see that? But we're not,
we're just conzing. So this has got to return us a list. So $3 is
to be a list of something. So, to me, it seems like the first one is probably the correct answer.
Does everybody see that? So, let's look at that clearly and just make sure. So, if we assume that
xs is a list of x, well, that helps with the nil, right? We know that that would work. And then this
could be x and a list of x, right?
Notice the names are y and y of s,
but we're going to call f of y to get something of type y,
and we're going to con it with a list of y.
I think that makes sense to me.
We have to, of course, pass the function.
This ys has to be the same type as xs,
so yeah, I'm going to go with the first one.
Okay.
I'll submit this and see if we got more.
I did it last night, Bob, and I got them all right.
So let's hope I didn't click the wrong one like I did last week.
And I got them all.
Good.
That last one could be maybe a little trickier.
So that's the quiz.
All right.
So for the next hour, what I want to do is all review for the midterm.
I especially want to make sure that we review the questions on the study guide
that have to do with formal semantics and then we'll pick up some other ones. If
you're specific questions that anybody has on the study guide, feel free to let
me know but I want to start with those two first. Does that make sense?
so check what it's doing
OK
so the first one we'll do is number four
make sure I got the right one.
Yep.
All right.
So, pattern matching, you're going to match an object.
So this word shapes is commonly used when we talk about what something looks like.
We call that a shape.
Usually we use that in talking about types.
So the first matching case is picked.
So that's just saying that it always picks the first thing that it matches.
Each of these, I've seen these referred to as arms.
each case is referred to as an arm. These are actually considered functions.
So we bind to the variables that are used in the cases.
So here we're deconstructing Xs, which is our list.
And we have looking at this case here, there's a head element with a tail,
which is another list of ins.
It's just a bunch of stuff that might be useful to think about when you're studying this.
Okay.
So then the question asks, we have this definition f.
This is not the one that I thought I was gonna do.
I thought we were doing the third question.
I meant to do number three.
Well, let's finish this and go back and do number three, since I already started talking
about it.
I got halfway into discussing it
and I was like, why am I doing this?
We said we were gonna do that.
We'll do this as a warm up.
My bad, got offline.
Because there's a number four which means
week four next to it, that's why I've been bad.
So we got this function.
What does this function do?
Just like we've been talking about with the quizzes.
We match on this thing.
We got an empty list
And we have this case here where we just looks like we take y and
then we recursively call this function, except it does something but
it doesn't do anything meaningful, right?
It actually deconstructs the list and constructs a new list.
Does that make sense?
It's almost like a contrived question, because who would ever write code this, right?
So if I evaluate this expression f of list 1, 2, 3,
Which answer do I get?
It's pay, isn't it?
It's pay.
Because after you've been destructed,
when you reach the end it repits another set of fluids back to the end of it.
Aha!
Yes it is.
This is question 4, right?
Yeah.
Huh?
Yes, the answer key's wrong.
You are absolutely right.
Good catch.
So I'm glad we did this.
It was worth it.
So I'm like, yeah.
When we get to the end, oh, but wait a minute.
No.
The answer key is not wrong.
So when we get to the end, that's the trick.
This is a little bit of a trick.
What happens when we get to the end?
if we matched on nil, and we're matching xs on nil, then xs had to be nil, so this is nil.
Even though it's not stated to be nil, but it's, this is, it's not intended to trick you.
It tricked me just now because you threw that at me, and I was like, oh yeah, yeah, yeah, wait a minute.
Let's think carefully.
So when we get, when we match on this case nil, that means this had to be empty.
Correct.
So, mill is the empty list, so this would end up being.
You could actually place this with mill,
so it is not going to be A.
It's E.
It's E. That's why I started by saying,
this function doesn't do anything.
I also have an answer .
So, everybody see that?
Every time you recursively call the function,
you're re-binding this parameter here.
In the new stack frame, you call the new function,
you have a new stack frame, this variable now
has something else that's referring to something else.
It's a different occurrence of that variable.
Did you really see that?
Very subtle.
Thank you for making me think I'm at E.
Wait, so is it A or E?
It is E.
Oh, okay.
Oh, that makes sense.
Right, because you matched on nil,
so this had to be nil.
Yeah.
Great.
So it was worth it.
And now we'll do number three.
Any other questions before I move on?
All right.
Number three.
Oh boy.
Lots of stuff here.
So this gives you some blurb about formal operational semantics, which is what we're
talking about.
Remember, these are called judgments, with these arrows here.
So when you have E produces a value B. E stands for expression complex.
We used E. And then we pass around this variable store so we can look up variable values.
And when we create these semantics or we look at these semantics,
we have things called reduction rules.
And they tell us how one step is decomposed into smaller steps.
That's another way of saying what we talked about when we went through this last week.
The values and
the store updates produced in the premises above the horizontal line are combined into
a value and store and store.
Okay, and store, wait, that's the parse.
The values and store updates produced in the premises above the horizontal line are
combined into the value and store produced by the conclusion below the horizontal.
It does parse it just as little bit oddly.
So, here you have this rule for negation.
So, if you have an expression e that evaluates to a value b,
if you have minus e, you get minus the value of e.
So this is the rule for negation.
Then they have these things called deduction trees,
which combine multiple rules in sort of a tree format
to decompose a program from bottom to top.
That's why I always said, I said you always start with bottom.
And that describes how the values and store updates flow from top to bottom.
So if we look at the question here.
So these are the reduction rules that talk about number literals.
Variable lookup negations, comparisons, and conditions.
So that's what all this stuff here.
So here's our conditional, greater than equal, number, variable lookup, negation.
Now we have a deduction tree.
So that's this part here.
This whole thing here is a deduction tree.
And remember, we start here.
Look at this.
This is the program we're trying to evaluate.
We're going to go up the tree.
So in order for us to evaluate this, we need a rule and that's what we're looking for.
What is this rule here?
If false.
So we think it's if false.
Okay.
I haven't actually parsed through all of this so let's look at this.
So this is saying v is going to end up being 0.
So here we have...
Yes, since v equals 0, it's false.
Right?
So that's the clue there.
So this is the if false.
So very good.
All right.
And then since it's false, then we only need this part of the expression, not this here.
We don't need to look up what x contains.
We need to go over here.
So, we're going to get three and in order for us to do this here,
we have to negate something.
So this is going to be negating.
Everybody see that?
If the clue here is that you have this minus sign here.
If you had x and when you look it up you get minus three,
And if you have minus x, you get positive 3.
So that's the negation rule we just talked about.
And then we need to still fill in.
So we can start looking at the answer.
So 1 is going to be a false.
So it's going to be b, c, or e.
And then we just did 3 was negation.
So we have c or e.
Everybody follow me?
You did that right.
Catch me if I'm wrong.
Okay, so we have C or E.
So we still need to fill in two and four.
Yeah, four is going to be looking up a variable, right?
Because if you had x and we got a value three, right?
So that means we look in the store.
So four is going to be bar.
So that doesn't help us any.
So we have to just look at 2.
So what is this rule?
So if we have, oh, we have, yeah, this is our var here,
and this is our number here.
So this 2 has got to be greater than or equal to 0.
So this is going to be the greater than or equal to rule.
So we're stuck with 8.
I think that is the answer.
Oh, I wrote it there.
Yep.
Did everybody see that?
Yeah, go ahead, Michelle.
I guess this might be a question you can't answer.
I hope so.
I'll try.
Go ahead.
On the test, are we also going to get all the rules for formal science ethics, or should
ethics or should me pay extra attention to studying that?
I don't think it would.
I'm not asking you to memorize the rules.
And I think somebody asked me this last quarter, and I double checked afterwards.
But I'll double check again.
So I'll let you know in Discord if I'm lying to you.
But I believe the answer is I will always give you the- I haven't looked at the questions
in like 10 to 11 weeks.
But I believe the answer is I'm always going to give you what the rules are so you can
actually be different.
I might actually ask you to define the rule,
but give you the actual symbols and have you tell me what it is.
.
But I'm not asking you to memorize those.
I wouldn't ask you to draw a deduction tree with some set of rules that we talked about in class that you can't see in front of you.
I don't think that's very.
Good question.
And I'll check that tomorrow night.
Alright.
So then the other one on the midterm study guide that covers this stuff is 18.
Let's make sure I get the right one.
Oh, before we do that, actually, let's just look at the solution strategy.
So this just tells you to match the conclusion below the horizontal line and
the premises above the horizontal line, with the rules.
So look for the patterns.
That's really what it comes down to.
And they don't have any variations here.
Sometimes we have variations so there is no variations.
Alright, so we'll go to 18.
This is a lot of the same verbiage here, just to help you if you're looking at this page.
probably the same judgments, reduction rules, decomposition in steps.
A little explanation of how it all works.
Again, we have the rule for negation, and it's exactly the same thing, right?
This question is asking you, instead of what we did before,
the stuff under, it looks like it's always under the line for a rule. So this is a little
different, right? It's not asking you to identify the rule. This time we tell you the rule and
then we ask you to identify what you fill in here. All right, so how do we tackle this?
Let's have to fill in what one, two, and three are.
Actually, I have a question.
One of the horizontal lines is missing an annotation, the one above, like, two.
Is it supposed to be add?
that's a good question I'm not sure so
you're right it's missing it's missing
something there so let's see if we can
figure out let's kind of look what's the
way I want you to think about these
that's a great question let's come back
to it because we're going to work our way
there so we're gonna start the bottom
right? So if you look at the bottom this is the program that we're executing. So
we have an assignment, we have addition, we also have addition, so this y equals
y plus 1 and then we have this conclusion that the answer is 10 and
then we updated our variable so yeah it looks to me like it is add right? Like so
So if we kinda go this way,
we have four plus y equals y plus one,
and we need to fill in this three thing.
Then y equals y plus one.
Here we have, we're updating y to get six.
And then over here, y starts out at five.
And this is one, so if we looked up y in our variable store
store, and we got five, and then we looked up one.
I'm sorry.
We have the number one, just the literal number one,
so five plus one is going to be six, so filling this in.
Yeah, I think you're right.
I think it's an add.
Does everybody see that?
Because if you just read it out,
what are we doing here?
We're going this way, and we're adding.
So, that means that number two should have something
about 6. It's not going to be the 20, so we can probably throw the letter D away. So it's
going to be this for 2. All right. Luckily, that's all we have to do for 2, so we can
move on and think about the other ones. So 1 is going to be number, right? So they're
all the same, we said. Oh, sorry. That's going to be a four, so it's not going to be the one
where, ooh, four evaluates to six. I don't think so, so that one's out, right? A is out.
So what have we eliminated? A and D, and we can also eliminate E. So Kishan says eliminate E,
and I think I see why.
This one is asserting that four evaluates to seven.
Maybe in quantum computing, but not here.
Not in this kind of computing.
So we're left with B and C, right?
Okay.
And then the only difference, if you look at these,
you see these are the same.
The only difference here is this thing in three, right?
So what the heck is this A?
In answer choice B, we have this A over here.
Do you see an A anywhere in this program?
If we look at the program, this is the actual program.
This is the output of the program, right?
Or the result.
It's not just the output, it's the output plus the state change to the variables.
But if we think about that, like, there is no such thing as A,
capital A, anywhere in here, right?
Right, so that's thrown in there to maybe throw you off, I don't know.
I didn't write the question, I inherit these, but I use them.
So I think we're left with C because that's the only one that makes sense.
So let's just validate that.
The only thing we didn't talk about is the 3, right?
So if we get 4 plus y equals y plus 1.
Remember, when we do an assignment,
the value of the entire expression is the value that we computed before assigning, right?
So y plus 1 is gonna be 6.
So 4 plus 6 is 10.
And that's how we get to the 10 here, so 3 is, that looks like it's right.
And y got 6 because 5 plus 1 got 6.
So it all kind of matches up to what we would expect.
So again, all of this stuff is just, this is the program,
you know how programs execute.
You know what, you've done enough programming now,
you know kind of what happens, and so what this is doing is providing you a
formal way to describe it. And that was a very good catch that this line is missing
the add rule, so very stupid. All right, any questions?
So there's the solution strategy which describes like what we did, how we reason
through it, there are no variations here.
So with these, this is pretty much the kind of question
you're going to get.
It's hopefully not too hard.
It's hopefully something that's just about reasoning
about what's the program doing.
Relying on your intuition about how the programs execute
and then being able to visually see the patterns.
I agree that maybe having all the symbols
drives you a little bit nuts right?
But the point of all this is to give you this idea
that when we talk about these things
and when we do formal semantics,
this is the kind of thing that they use
in computer science literature.
So when you study master's in CS,
this is something you may encounter.
Okay.
So those are the two that I definitely wanted to cover.
Now, were there any specific ones that anybody wants to go over?
I'll go over one, whatever, but yeah, if you want to go there's number 17.
Number 17, okay.
Let's take a look, I'm going to turn to it here.
I just want you to talk through it.
Talk through it.
Okay.
Matter matching and recursion.
Do you have a specific question or
you just want me to talk through it?
I just want you to talk through it.
Talk through it?
Okay.
So, this is similar to what we were just doing on the quiz with the dollar one,
I'm sorry, the question one, question two, the types.
So G is some kind of a, looks like it's probably a function because we're gonna
call it and we're gonna pass it some stuff.
And over here we have $2, this is gonna return,
what do we think it's gonna return?
Some kind of a what?
What is the clue here?
Some, A list.
A list, good call.
So it's a list because of the cons here, right?
Did everybody see that?
All right.
So we're taking two things.
It looks like we're taking, what are we matching?
Oh, xs, ys.
Okay, oh, wait, we have two lists, right?
So we're saying if we think about this,
what we're actually doing is creating a tuple here, right?
We're creating a tuple with the two lists in it.
So, the type of xs is what?
List int.
List int, right.
The type of ys is?
Also list int.
So the type of this thing is what?
I don't know.
List int.
Well.
Mm-hm.
So it's a tuple, where the first element is a list of int,
and the second element is a list of it.
So it's what we call a two-tuple.
So it's not, this in and of itself is not a list.
It's two lists paired together as a tuple.
Which is why when we match on this thing,
notice it's got nil-nil.
Well nil is a list of something, right?
And a nil is a list of something.
That's why this works, right?
So we have a, well we think it works because we could have, we could have non-compilation,
right, so that's one of the choices here.
So, all right, what do we got?
We have, if this were, let's keep going with this line of reasoning, a list event, a list
event, we're matching, we don't hit the nil cases.
We have this case and this case.
Does this look complete, by the way?
Okay.
What if one of them is nil and the other one is not?
So what I just basically am getting at here is, in this case here you have at least one
element on the left side list or the xs list.
They're not really positional, not left and right.
They are positional, they're 0 and 1.
That's a list where the head is A and the tail is B.
The head is A and the tail is B.
And this is a list where the head is C and the tail is D.
So the tail is gonna be a list, right?
And these two heads are gonna be what?
It's, they have to be it's.
Yeah.
If they weren't it's,
then these couldn't be lists, right?
So whenever you have this consting, you have a head of whatever type is inside the list.
So int, int, and then this is list event, list event.
So what's missing is, what if one of them is nil and the other one is not?
I don't know that that...
I don't know if the compiler is going to yell at me.
Wait, if you're adding A and D, isn't D a list so you can't add them?
Yes.
Let me come back to that.
Keyshawn, did you have something else?
You both talked at the same time.
I was going to say that if one list is null but the other isn't, I would think it either just doesn't do anything or it presutes as an error.
It's a match error.
Yeah.
That's what I was getting at with that line of discussion, is that we're missing a case, right?
Okay.
But then someone online, I forget who, was it Cindy?
Was it you?
Yep.
Okay, yeah.
And you were saying, wait a minute.
Hold on.
Hold the phone.
You're calling g and you're passing a and d.
And we just said that d had to be a list event.
And if you look at g, the function would have to take two ints, right?
So, if we go down to what the question is actually asking here.
Notice it's passing add as the function.
So that's an int in the second parameter.
And what Cindy has observed is that, when I call G here, well, A is an int.
Okay, that's okay, but remember this is abstracted out, but when I call this, D has to also be
an int.
Everybody see that?
So this won't compile.
See if that's the answer I have.
That's the answer right.
This won't compile.
You can actually put that in the repl to see.
I believe it will complain here where you call it.
This code compiled, yes.
There is no way of filling in the types.
So not only do we have a potential match error
if it did compile, remember that a match error is,
Is that a compile time error or a runtime error?
It's runtime.
I wanna double check and make sure
that the code does compile then.
I think it will.
But I can't remember.
I think it will best effort.
So, let's go to...
I'm just making up names.
I'm doing this because I have to delete the line numbers from the name.
I'm gonna just copy this and...
Try to paste it. I think...
Oh, it won't even compile. Oh, right, because I have to change this. So I would have to change
g
to be a function that takes int int
and produces an int.
And then I would need to change $2 to be a list of int, I think.
And that will compile even though it won't compile.
It doesn't even like C.
So we have more problems.
So we never even got that far, right?
So we see this here.
It's trying to call itself, so passing g and then b and c.
So that's also a problem, because we would need to pass b in d.
So we'd have to actually change this.
Because look, look at the types here.
This is a list event.
That's a list event.
b is a list event, OK.
But c is not a list event, but it's an in.
So this whole thing has all kinds of problems.
I just find it a little interesting
that it doesn't catch on the d first.
It just .
Well, it actually did here.
Because now that I gave it types, remember in Scala 2,
you also have to have Scala as well.
Scala 2, Scala 3, sorry.
Remember in Scala as well, you always
have to have parameters on your arguments, on your, sorry.
You have to have, I said the wrong word.
you have to have type annotations on your parameters.
You have to assert that this g is a specific type.
This is a function that takes a tuple of two ints.
I'm sorry, this is a function that takes two ints
and returns an int.
And this is a list event.
And in our question, we didn't even have types assigned.
We asked you to read it.
So in this case, I tried to do this.
but I would need to have switched this parameter so far.
We could do it.
It should compile if I change this to instead of b.
So that needs to be a b, and then this needs to be a d.
I think that would be a b.
Now it still doesn't like it.
Because it found a list event, and it needs an int.
Oh, because I didn't change that.
Oh, right, so we would need to change this to C.
So yeah, that's why it's all kinds of problems,
because everything's out of place.
So even if I did that,
now I'm going to get this warning,
which is not a compiler error,
but it does come out of the compiler.
That's what I was going for,
because I was like, obviously we have problems.
This is like when I grade data structures exams.
I have to type everybody's code in
and make little corrections,
and then like minus one for that,
and oh, it's awful.
So I took this right and what I started to do is, I started to refine the original code
to get it to someplace that did compile.
This compiled but it's a warning, so you could actually run this.
And then if you tried to call, I'd have to define add, so let's do that.
and then I can call it and it will probably...
work, in this case, it would work.
But again, with what we had before,
remember, I changed this, right, I changed this.
But with what we had before, it wouldn't have worked.
There's all kinds of problems, all kinds of wrong,
as my brother used to say.
When you try to, like say you just do the same thing.
Get rid of the integers inside of the list.
Yeah.
Or it would just, it's already telling you in the morning
that it would fail.
But what type of error would you want?
When you say get rid of the integers inside of the-
Like you still say, list, like say you get rid of 2 and 1
that's inside of that statement.
Here?
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah so if you get rid of those and you run it through,
that list is considered new, isn't it?
So I think what you're saying is, get rid of these?
Yes.
Like that?
And then if you run it, it would get an error.
It would give us a match error.
Very good, yeah, that's what I was getting at before.
So the compiler complained and said,
this is a problem because you're gonna end up
with match errors, potentially,
depending on the inputs you supply.
And here we supplied an input that sure enough
produced a match error.
So yeah.
When you're working with this stuff,
you should be trying all this stuff out.
Like when you're working with the REPL
to try to wrap your brain around what's going on.
Yeah, good call.
So, any other questions about this question?
This is why we also say give us the best answer, right?
So, that's not intended to trick you,
but the bottom line doesn't compile with D.
It was interesting though, pattern matching error occurs.
You might be tempted to think it was that,
but you have to get through the compiler
before you can get that part.
All right, any other specific ones that folks wanna do?
So it's 17, so I'll check that on.
Okay let's try number eight. I'm gonna just fill the time between now and break
with this stuff. So if you have if you want to scan ahead and tell me if this
after we do one if there's one you want to see and then we'll go.
So more pattern matching. By the way this one covers like week two and week three
so that's why I picked it.
I was trying to pick the ones that covered the most material.
Ah, so decompose a list, I say that all the time.
Or deconstruct is usually how I say it, but same idea.
All right, so we have this function called skip head.
And take head.
You have two functions.
So we look at skip head, what does it do?
Well, we get a list and if we're empty,
then we just return empty and if we have some head value and
a tail, we call take head on the tail.
So we actually don't care about the head element,
so we throw it away.
So then we call it take head.
All right, so in the case where we have an empty list,
we return the empty list.
In the case where we have a head, we keep the head,
and then we skip the head.
Oh, this looks like we're going to be doing something
like keeping some elements and taking some elements
and skipping some elements.
that's starting to kind of come into focus
as we kind of process through this.
So we start with this function, or this expression, sorry.
Skiphead, and we have a list.
The rain in Spain.
And if we look at the way this will proceed
as we try to evaluate this expression,
what are we gonna do?
We're starting with skiphead.
So they're always, we're gonna start by
So, skipping the first element, right?
So the goes away.
We bind, well we don't bind.
It doesn't bind to anything.
We don't care.
And then we're left with rain in Spain in a list.
That's the tail.
And so we pass that tail in the take head.
So now we have rain in Spain.
So we have rain, and then a list of in Spain.
So we're gonna keep rain, then we're gonna go back to skip head.
then we're going to throw away in,
and then we'll call take head on that single element list,
in Spain, and then we'll match on this case,
and we'll return,
we'll return Spain, cons with skip head,
and this is nil, right, because we're at the end,
so ys is nil, so when we call skip head
And the input parameter is nil.
We'll match on this case, and so we'll end up
with rain spain.
Does everybody see that?
I hope it's not too hard.
So let's see.
Is that the answer that I have for eight?
Yes, B.
So there's these variations here.
You could change up, try on your own when you're studying,
try changing these up and seeing what happens.
So in this case, if we're changing skiphead, and when we do that,
we're actually, oh, we're gonna need to have at least two elements.
You might start introducing possible match errors, right?
because you might end up with cases that are missing.
So you can start thinking about that.
In skip head, we could also, oh, so this
is just having you add multiple elements.
And what it's basically doing is changing the meaning of skip
head to skip two at the head, if that's even possible,
or skip three at the head.
So we've established that we'd probably be able to compile if we're missing cases.
So if we tried this one, we had the reign in Spain.
This would match the reign and then YS would be in Spain.
So we would take in and all we would be left with is in, right?
Everybody see that?
just reason about what the function's look like.
What about that last term?
I think take head.
Right.
So in take head, we're changing this case here to, let's see.
Oh, OK, so this time, we keep take head,
we leave take head the way it was, but then what we do
is we actually are appending to a list.
So we're going to call skip head and we're going to append to a list,
single element list that has y.
So when we bound the head there, so this will actually,
what do you think it would be?
So our .
I'm thinking it would be .
It would be .
It's reversed.
This is the same, by the way, as triple colon.
Triple colon, we did that earlier, right?
That was, we had that one question where we had a list of a single element,
we were appending this double plus does the same thing.
Did you have further questions?
Sorry, you kept talking.
Sorry.
Just wanted to make sure.
So you see it.
So the skip head is going to return a list, right?
And this is going to, instead of putting the y at the beginning.
Sorry, this one here, the y at the beginning.
It's going to put it at the end, but it's going to be contained in a list,
single element.
So that's eight. I've got another one picked out we can do, or you all may suggest one?
I guess I have just a quick question.
Sure, no, go ahead.
No, number six.
Number six, sure.
It's really just a linked list can't have more than one type installer, right?
because I was thinking about it getting errored because you can't have...
Oh, this one here?
Yeah.
Should we read the question first, or do you want me to answer that?
You can read the question first.
All right, so the question...
It starts by reminding you about the cons.
This cons operator, those are methods declared in classes.
Remember, that's gonna be defined in the list class.
Top level class, that's called Any.
That's equivalent to, it's actually higher than, so we usually have AnyRef,
which is equivalent to java.lane.object.
I think there's somewhere.
I'm gonna stop and just do this quick because it's there,
So we may as well make sure.
So this is saying there's something called any
at the top of the hierarchy, and we have anyVal and anyRef.
And this thing corresponds to java.lang.object.
it's that all Java reference types, remember we're running on the Java
platform so all Java reference types have object as a superclass so we have
anyRef is the equivalent of that and eval is going to end up because for
efficiency reasons you're going to have int, float, double,
And so forth.
There's probably short, there's other Boolean,
it's there, I did it.
All right, but that's what this is saying.
So this line here, the Scala class hierarchy has a top level class,
any that is a super class of all simple and reference types.
Simple types, reference types.
So we have this expression, and it looks like what we're doing is we've got nil, and then
we're, remember this is gonna go from this direction, so we're gonna associate to the
right.
That's the right way to say that.
So we're gonna call a method cons on nil, and we're gonna cons seven to it.
we're gonna take that list and call cons and we're gonna cons the stream s i x onto that
and then we're gonna take that thing that list and we're gonna cons onto the front of
it five and I know what you're doing with your question.
So, I'm guessing you have an idea what you think the answer is?
Yeah, I thought the answer would be because a string wouldn't be a simple reference detector.
All right.
And did you try this out in the REPL?
I did not.
You did not.
Let's do it.
So that would be my suggestion when you are encountered, like when studying,
when you encounter a question like this,
is to stick it in the REPL and see what it does, right?
So take this.
And I'll fire up my REPL.
And you will find that it compiled.
And notice what it did.
So the thing contained inside the list
is a compound type or a sum type,
it's either an int or a string.
And so this is valid in SCALA.
So what you're sort of getting at
is that very rarely,
so your intuition is correct,
but the answer to the question is,
it's a little bit of a trick,
but what's happening here is that we're used to dealing
with lists that have a single kind of thing in it, right.
So we either have like ints or we have strings,
but usually not both, right?
Scala doesn't have this.
So if you do that, if I say xs.head,
it's going to give me five,
but it's going to give me the type is int or string,
because at this point it doesn't know anymore, right?
So now I can do res0.asInstanceOfInt.
Actually, this touches on what we'll cover in lecture today.
So this is a cast when I do asInstanceOf.
This is a cast.
If I said asInstanceOfString, I get a class cast exception
because I can't just take an int and cast it to a string.
I would have to do some sort of conversion on it.
So if I say, instead of that, I could do a conversion like map.
Does that work?
Maybe not.
It does work.
So I'm just using the conversion.
So if I say, instead of that, I could do a conversion like map.
I'm just using underscore, oh no, it doesn't work.
It's not a member of int or string.
So, oh, wait a minute.
That's probably not what I meant.
I meant this, there's no map.
If I call plain old two string,
remember, Java has two string on everything,
so we'll get something.
But no.
Back to the original question,
this expression here is perfectly valid
and we get this sum type here.
So that would mean, going back to the question,
this answer is not correct
because we did not see a type checking error.
So the list's length 4?
It be or is that?
Okay, it be three.
Why is it not four?
Because no would be counted as a particle.
That's right.
Nil has length zero and is sort of the marker for the end of the list.
Yeah.
So this one here, let's see, six.
The correct answer is E, which is what you said the length would be three.
The other answer is it's not four and it's not two because we know it's three.
And then the other one was type check neurons because neurons are in the spring, so we did
that.
Did I get them all?
Oh, because nil is not an integer.
That's just a bogus answer.
That's just like wrong, like that's true that nil is not an integer, but
that isn't why a type checking error occurs.
All right, so we need six.
Other ones you wanna do?
Did you think of the variation?
First it looked like-
Yeah, sure.
Where it's just like nil, every, the third one?
The third one, you wanna look at this one, so.
Well, I want to do the first-hand point, but I'm more interested in the third.
You're more interested in the third, so we're changing this here to that.
Okay.
What happens?
I would think that it just creates a completely empty list.
There's nothing there.
It's trying to do something, but it's failing.
Okay.
So it just does nothing
because it's not technically wrong.
I'm guessing you didn't replicate this.
I did not.
So we got a list of lists,
a list of empty lists.
Right.
So what we have is two elements.
So we have an empty list.
We have a head element for this part.
We just ignore this part with a list of nothing.
Right.
And then we const that with a list of nothing.
So we have a list of nothing and a list of nothing.
So in a sense, like the nil create,
Because it's using nether creates too much for lists.
Well, no, let's see, let's do.
If I do that, I get a list of two elements, five and six.
So, this is perfectly legal to treat this as a list of whatever, or a list of whatever.
And so that's a list, that's a list, and then now I'm terminating my outer list.
It's a little bit weird. But relate it to something like that, which you're more
likely to see, and then try to see what's going on like with what what is how is
it interpreting this and how to interpret that. Nobody ever does things
like this, this is very intronite, but it's an exam right so I might do that, I don't know.
The key is understanding that, so what's actually happening.
Okay, what's actually happening is you have nil and you're calling cons.
cons and passing nil.
And then you're taking that whole thing
and calling cons and passing nil.
That's what it's actually doing.
So this is the end of your list,
because that's we associate from the right
when you have this thing, you have this expression, no, no.
No.
Oops, I'm not writing it all the way out.
could be easy.
You have no.
No.
Ugh.
Spelling.
No.
Again, spelling.
All right.
So, oh you know what?
I'm going to do it this way.
Watch this.
I'll do it all over again
but this time I'll make it more.
This is the classic use case.
I am going to spell that with two L's.
I don't know why.
It has to do with my mind thinking about Nulls.
Sorry.
I'll keep my cons is like this.
Okay.
So the reason I did that is to relate it to what I was trying to do before.
So I do mil dot colon colon colon.
And then inside there goes the green one.
And then that was the red one.
So we're associating from right to left.
And as we said, the con's operator is implemented as a method.
So you start with the blue one, and we go right to left.
So we're calling dot, double colon, and then we're passing the green one.
And then that's going to give me back a list,
and now I'm calling dot, double colon, and I'm passing the red one.
So what is, if you think about that, I started with an empty list,
and now I const it with an empty list,
I got a list of, how does it do this?
Nil.type.
Yeah, this is the way Scala does this.
I think of it like that, but that won't actually compile.
But it does Nil.type, so I'll write that in.
Usually when I'm doing this, when I'm working,
and this won't compile, I'm like,
oh, this is that case where I have to do dot type
because this is a singleton object thing.
All right, and then I'm like, I don't care,
just compile, dang it.
All right, so that's a list of nil,
and then I'm conzing with nil,
so the whole thing is a list of nil.
This one here is always like the
marker for the end and then everything else is just an element.
Just like in our five six case.
This is our marker for the end and everything here is an element.
And it's breaking it all the way down into the smallest possible chunk.
So you had asked about the other one, was it this, the first one?
Yes.
So this one we're changing this to...
Oh, okay.
Oh.
I think it's the same.
So let's see.
Yeah.
That's the same as what we had before.
This is the type int or string.
And it was five.
It's not printing the quotes, but that's six of the string.
And then it's seven int.
and the original one had the same thing.
So this is the same as saying no.
You can also do,
I think that works too.
Was there any real reason to do that
over just writing them?
Over using nil?
Yeah.
Most people wouldn't, most people would use nil.
I think the naming nil comes from like, when people talk about higher order programming
in languages like Haskell, they use the nil.
That's part of Haskell for the empty list.
So I think people who are doing Scala functional programming would like it to feel like what
they're used to thinking about, so that's why they define it as nil.
But we got three minutes before break time.
Why don't we just...I don't think we have enough time to do another one.
I want to make sure to get through the new material.
So, we will stop there and then come back at 7.30 and then we'll pick up the new stuff
for time.
All right.
It's so good to be done.
Just like this, I'm going to be able to play and play with the other people.
I'm going to be able to play some more and more.
So I'm going to play some more.
I love you.
So, I'm going to put it on the table.
I was going to put a beer on the table.
I thought it was a good idea.
I thought it was really weird.
But it was really, it was really hot.
We will be back at the end of the video, but we will be back to the video.
I will be back to the video.
I will be back to the video and I will be back to the video.
I got a couple of minutes here.
I'm going to get a little bit of a sandwich.
I have no idea how to make a product.
I use a product for this product.
I don't like to make a product for this product.
I've used a product for this product.
So, let's do this.
So, let's do that.
Thank you.
All right.
Okay, please.
Good morning.
All right.
Thank you.
So, I would leave the second side and put the shape here, so I was going to move it.
So, I decided to cut the shape of the shape.
I just did the shape of the shape.
I'm going to add it.
To be continued...
I also use 3 times a day.
I use the same size as it is.
I use it as a little as it is.
It's a little bit better than I use.
I need to add the
water to the water.
It is a very good source of water.
I have to add to the water.
Now I'm going to put on it.
Okay.
so
and this is how it works, so I'm going to get a little bit more
and I'm going to go over here.
I think it's a nice little bit of a knife.
I think it's kind of a nice knife.
I'm going to do this.
It's a nice knife.
so
All right, let's see.
To be continued...
um
So, let's see what we did.
I am going to go ahead and get started.
Do you know how to use the
I'm going to put the camera on the camera.
Thank you.
So, it's just a little piece of paper.
It's just a little bit.
I'm not sure what I'm doing.
I'm not going to have a look at it.
I usually use this.
I usually use a little more than water.
So I usually use a little more than water.
I usually use water to put the water in a little bit.
I also use water to put it in a little bit.
I use water to put it in a little bit.
It is very delicious.
I use water to add water to water.
Now, I use water to put it in a little bit.
I use water to put it in a little bit.
All right.
Well, we'll get started with our new material.
Again, this stuff is not on the midterm.
Also, I forgot to note before, there is no homework this week, just your study guide.
So, study guide is intended to prepare you for the midterm, so I want you focused on
that.
It is worth, well, that midterm and final study guides are worth 10% of your grade,
So I expect you to do them.
It will be apparent to me if you used AI to give you answers and then took the exam and
bombed it like I can usually tell.
So spend your time wisely.
Study the material in the study guide.
Please put questions in Discord.
We were having a discussion among faculty about how students aren't using office hours
anymore or Discord conversations anymore to get help.
And I'm not saying anybody here is necessarily doing it, but it seems like everybody likes
to use AI to get answers.
I do it in my own life as a programmer, but we do have real people that we can talk to
in our Discord server or come to the office hours.
so if you're struggling with anything
please do reach out
and don't be scared
to put it in discord
a lot of times people are like well if I put it in discord
I might look bad
we're all here to learn together so I don't think
anybody here, hopefully
we're not going to judge each other for asking
questions because
no question is a bad question
in my opinion
anyway so just
some food for thought, there's also no quiz
next week for this
next week. The next homework and quiz will be due the week after the midterm. So focus your time
and study. All right, I rearranged the material because we were talking about nil and I thought,
well maybe we could do option types first and then we'll get into some of these other topics
later. So we'll start with option types. It's a little bit more natural, given that we were just
talking about lists and nil and what does that mean.
Okay so what do we do when we get to a place where we are missing data? So in
this code here on the left we have some triple question marks. So what do we have?
we have find, so this is a function, or I guess a method because it's a death. And we get a list
of x and we have a p, and notice p is taking an x and then returning bullion, so we can think of
this as a predicate, that's why it's called p actually. And we're looking at our list and
we're saying well if we're empty, what do we do? We're trying to find something, and we reach the
end of the list and we didn't find it so what what should we do there we can't
return nil right because nil is a list and the return type is X right so that's
that would be a problem okay notice the rest of the function here it's like well
if I have a head followed by something else like the rest of the list then if
If I found it, so this is my predicate,
I call my predicate function.
And if that returns true, then we found it.
So we say x.
We found 0.
And otherwise, we just keep going.
We keep going down through the rest of the list.
At the end, we're looking to see what our result is.
And if our result is, if we're looking for the number, say,
42, if it's a list of ints, and we find it,
well, then we would assert that here,
we would say that result double equal 42 as our contract.
If we didn't find it, then what should we do?
All right.
So over here on the right, we also have another function.
This is called reduce.
Reduce is doing something like, looks like we've got a list of x, and
and we're calling f, and when we call f,
we're passing two elements of type x, two instances of type x.
So notice reduce is going to return x, so this type checks.
And if we get to the end of the list,
there's nothing to combine.
So what do we do?
Again, we can't return nil.
So this is a problem.
So we have missing data.
So this is one option.
So we could say, well, if we have nil, we could return null.
We're used to this in Java land.
We use null all the time.
But now that means that our contract and our clients,
clients or calling code, have to distinguish
between null and some non-null result.
So we would have to add code every time we use this
to figure that out.
We could also do the other thing that we often
do in Java, which is throw an exception.
I think in some of the stuff we've done,
we would see maybe a no such element exception
if we ran out of elements.
So this is kind of bad, though.
How would you write the exception contract?
Well, if you think about it, if you're
going to throw an exception.
Actually, by default, if you use triple question mark,
literally, just what you see there, it will throw an element.
I'm sorry.
Throw an exception.
Not implemented error is the name of that exception.
So you'd have to actually do what?
What do you do in Java when you might get an exception?
Anybody remember?
There's a construct in Java that we use when we might have an exception.
Try catch.
Try catch, right.
And Scala has a try catch, so you could do that.
Okay, so what we're going to do here is we're going to come up with a way to represent missing
results, and we'll call these things option types.
So what is an option type?
it is as what you would think. It's an optional value. You might have a value and you might
not have a value. So it's a principled approach to missing data. So an option T is very similar
to a list of T, but with a list we would have some arbitrary length. It could be zero. It
could be any length. With an option, you either have one element of type T or no element of
of type t. So with a list, we have basically two options. We have nil and we have cons.
In an option, we have two options. We have none, which represents the absence of data,
and we have sum, which represents the presence of data. So here's some example expressions
that are of type option int.
So none would mean that we have no int.
And then sum five would mean that we have an int
with a value five.
So this is what it looks like if we program with null.
I can't remember if this would actually compile.
This looks kind of weird to me
because of that null that's there,
So we're gonna actually see what happens.
This will compile, I think.
Yes, so we could call as instance of,
which is, as I said earlier, that's a cast.
So you're taking null and you're casting it to an X.
So that'll work.
But then you have to, of course, deal with what happens if you actually get a null.
So if we say find int.
Oh, I need the...
I need the credit card.
Oh, that worked.
So that would give us an int of 0.
That's weird.
It must have cast the null to a 0.
That's really weird.
This is why we hate null.
So this is what happens when you program with an optional.
So instead of this kind of weirdness that even I don't remember what it does, we normally do this.
If I have a list that has no data in it, and I return none, and my return type here is option x.
So if I have something where I have x followed by something, remember if we do this, we're basically saying we'll only match on this case if this expression evaluates to true.
So we'll take the predicate P and apply it to X.
And if this matches, because we have a value that matches the predicate,
we'll return some X.
And if we have this here, rest dot is weird.
I think the dot's a typo.
That shouldn't be a dot.
So we have, you don't care.
Some had value in the rest.
Well, that means we didn't match on the previous case.
So if we didn't match on the previous case,
we'd just keep going until we hit the base case.
So this is how you program with optionals.
And notice the difference here is that your return type is x.
Here, your return type is option x.
So if I say to, this is usually when we see this,
like on here it means I'm saying to like an AI find x is greater than five and if found return
the string found x otherwise find x is greater than three and if found return found x and
otherwise print not found so if we we save this to an AI we can do it with client handling dull
And sometimes an AI will actually give you a couple of this.
So this is also that don't care shorthand.
Remember, we can do this as a shortcut for we
have an argument to a function.
And then we're using that argument once and throwing it away.
So this is the equivalent of x arrow x greater than 5.
That's our predicate function.
So if I get null, then I'm, oh, right.
So I'm saying find in my list anything,
find whichever element is greater than five, if there is one.
And if I get nothing back, then do it again,
and say, find for anything greater than three.
And then if I get nothing back, say not found.
so this implements the requirements.
Otherwise, I got some value.
Oh, notice that's a little bit iffy.
It says found x, but here it actually
has you splicing the value of x in.
It's a little bit different than what it says.
You might get this out.
So these two cases here, this outer one
is the case where we found 5, and this inner one
is the case where we found bigger than 5.
And this is the case we found bigger than 3,
but not bigger than 5.
So that's what this is showing you is the client.
So here we call find.
So we're the client code and we're handling null.
That's what this is showing.
If, on the other hand, we have an option, we can do this.
So we call find.
And then, because we get an option back, we can call or else.
So this is actually a function that's defined on the option type.
Or I should probably properly because of properly call that method.
So this is the option type that we get back from find and
then we call or else method on the option type.
And or else is gonna be implemented to actually return null,
I'm sorry, return none if the result is done.
So none will just return none.
And I'm sorry, I said that wrong.
If I got a sum back then I would just return the thing I got back.
Right?
And if I got a none back then I'm going to replace it with this expression which also
has to have type option .
So this will call the function once and then if it's returning none I call the function
again with my different .
and this time I can reduce what I'm printing.
My print cases are just both collapsed into this one here.
So much better.
So the compiler doesn't support null checking
and you can't call methods on null.
You get a null pointer exception.
We're used to that from Java.
Option also has map, fold, and filter.
So we have map, fold, and filter,
we're used to those on lists,
and we also have them on options.
Remember I said that options are very similar to lists,
except they just have one or zero elements.
So you can imagine that this is more
of a basic version of a list,
but it's much smaller because it's just
potentially one element or none.
So here's to talk about nested options.
So here we have a safe divide function.
So remember, dividing by zero returns, like, I don't remember what it does in Scala.
I think in Java you might get not a number.
I think in Scala you might get, let's see, 3 divided by 0.
What does it give me?
It complains in arithmetic exception by 0.
So here what I can do is check.
If I got a zero for the denominator, I can return none.
right? And if I got something other than zero from the denominator, I can
do the division and wrap it in a sum.
So there's also this function option.when and option is also option.unless.
So this when and unless is a way to pass a predicate.
So it will only do this part if this succeeds, so m not equals 0.
Otherwise it will return not, not n, right?
And unless is the opposite.
So unless m equals 0, return n divided by n,
I'm sorry, n divided by m, and then otherwise return n.
So if I have, if I wanted to divide an optional int safely, so I start off with this four,
and I want to divide by two, I can call map on my option.
So this is an option of an int.
It holds a four, in this case.
If I call map, remember that if I do this, this is just using the parameter, right?
So this is just shorthand.
and it's calling safeDivide.
So whatever is wrapped by this option, if anything,
is passed as the first parameter to safeDivide.
And that's going to return back an option,
so I'm going to get an option of an option of an int.
If I do that, if I call i.map and safeDivide with a 0,
I should get also an option of an option of an int.
In this case, because 4 can be divided by 2,
I'm going to get two.
It's going to be my answer.
And with this double wrapping.
And then over here, because I can't divide by zero,
I'm going to get none, right?
But we don't like nested options.
And if you remember, we had a function on lists,
a method on lists that we could use.
So we can say flat map.
And flat map will flatten this thing.
So if I have an option of an option of an int,
so if I took this and called flatten,
it would get back a single option wrapping in it.
Here, I can call flatten app.
And the return type of this thing has to be an option.
And this will just give me one flattened option.
We talked about nil at the end of the first half.
a lot because we were dealing with lists. So just sort of zooming out a little bit,
these are the kinds of emptiness we could have, so nill could be an empty list. Null
is an empty reference. None is an empty option and unit always has this, we represent, this
is the value that's represented by these two parens. These are the corresponding things.
So this is using null here because over in Java, oh, it's because it's using this code,
right?
So we have a sum, we have a list events, here we have a node and integers.
Remember in Java, when we do data structures to, we do linked lists by having these nodes,
and the nodes have a next element.
And the next element is null, and we're at the end.
And that's why we're seeing this here.
So in this code, the corresponding in Scala, we use nil for empty list.
and we use null to represent emptiness in a list here,
and null is always gonna be an empty reference, of course.
So that works.
Java added optional.
This is corresponding to our option in Scala.
In some languages they're called, options are called maybes,
like I think in Haskell they're called maybes.
And there's like, the sum version is like a just,
called it just and I think it's nothing is the corresponding thing to none so
there's different names in different languages for these things but Java has
optional empty and forget what they called it but it's non and then unit
corresponds to void which no return value we see void in Java you know we
would have unit in Scala.
So in Scala we hate null.
This is why I didn't know what to do with those slides
earlier, that thing that had null and as instance of.
I was like, well, what?
I forgot what that does.
We pretend null doesn't exist.
Null is horrible.
If you remember your experience learning Java,
if you did learn Java, I'm assuming you did,
null pointer exceptions were kind of annoying, right,
when they come up, you always have to check for null
all the time in Java.
And so people who like Scala hated that,
hated all that extra boilerplate code
that we had to write to do that.
So a lot of these more recent languages have none
being separate from null.
Swift and Kotlin have...
I think they use null for none.
I don't know which, I don't know what Kotlin does.
Yeah, they distinguish nullable and non-nullable types.
So here's what it looks like in Kotlin.
I've never done a thing in Kotlin,
so I can sort of reason about it.
This T question mark in Kotlin
resembles option T in Scala.
Null is used for none,
and types without question mark do not allow null.
There's like additional rules
that the compiler probably enforces.
Oh yeah, it says it over here.
So if I have a var A which is a string,
and I set it equal to ABC, and then I try to update A to be null,
it'll give me a compilation error,
because that is not a nullable type.
So the compiler actually catches that for you.
If I try to call a.length, then that would be safe.
It would always be safe.
In this case here, I can't call length
on something that's nullable.
So I get a compiler error there.
But I am allowed to update my b to contain null,
which is basically an empty option,
as we would think would come.
And then I guess they have this kind of syntax,
bbangbang.link, which probably tries to unwrap the option.
This would be like calling get on an option.
If you called get on an option, it will return something.
So if I have an option of x,
I think it's this, I have option x and I call and I say like val x equals and then I say
x.get, val y equals so y is going to have type x. So it's going to unwrap the option
And it will throw a no such element exception if it's a none.
So that's why you might get this exception here.
Same idea.
This could be a safe call.
So you're basically saying give me the length.
Oh, it shows you.
It explicitly expands it to this.
So if b is not null, b.length, otherwise null.
I'm getting confused already because of all the nulls
in this language that I don't use.
So then here you have safe call with default.
So this, oh, it's got this extra question mark colon over here.
So already now I'm looking up Kotlin syntax because I don't understand what I'm doing.
This is what it means explicitly expanded.
You don't have to really remember this.
This is just relating it to that language.
So here's our summary.
option type represents presence or absence of data
either type represents alternative results so we didn't talk about either
but either is defined usually as
I think we might see ethers later
in the course but like with option we have either something
or nothing or some or none I guess for either
we have either an A or a B
and this means that this is a sum type
actually so if I have sum
val x
either AB equals
and then sum code here
then I'm either going to have
this will actually be a left
A
left A
or right
B.
I'm using sort of
pseudo code here when I write this, but
it's either going to be a left
type or a right type.
Oftentimes in
production Scala code, you might see
either
E A.
The reason we do that is because this E denotes error.
So the convention, and it's not required,
but we usually put the error on the left.
And so we often say that either is right biased
because of the right one.
So a valid value would be a right A,
which is kind of corresponding to a sum A.
But what LEFT E would give you here is the ability to capture an error
but not have it throw an exception.
You can still retain what the error was.
So this is why we often use this in Corruption in Scala Code.
Then there's all kinds of variations on this theme in the cat's effect library.
But I don't remember what they all are.
There's all these ways you can chain the errors together
so if you have multiple errors, you can list them out
and report them to logs and whatever.
So our option and our either are going to support higher order functions. I might
have said a minute ago so either is going to be right bias. So map will map
a right to whatever it'll pass a function, it will operate on
an A. And if you have a left and you call map it'll just return whatever the
left is holding. It doesn't do any transformation. You can also call left map, which will actually
map the error or the thing on the left to some other value. So it's right biased.
This gives us the ability to do things like or else. So if I have an option and I call or else,
I'm going to get whatever. We saw this earlier, but if I have a none and I call or else,
that I'm going to get whatever I passed.
And actually, it's going to use non-strictness,
so it's not going to evaluate.
If we look at or else,
and I don't remember what it's actually called,
but if I say x,
I'm going to use this syntax,
option x.
And that's going to return
option
x.
So what's this doing? This syntax
here means that
x produces an option of x, but
it may not actually execute this because
this is non-strict.
So if I have
a sum
and I pass this expression,
this will be a thunk that never gets evaluated
and then it's a little bit more efficient.
So this is how
non-strictness shows up
in the wild. So, if you ever see that, like the syntax in Scala, that's what's
going on, so it won't actually evaluate. This is actually very useful.
If I go back like 26 years to when I was a newly minted programmer down the
street at the Chicago Board Options Exchange, we had a logging framework that
used to evaluate all of our strings, like we used to do string concatenation, and
it would build up all these strings and then it would like put them in log. But
But if you wanted to log something only in certain cases,
like if any of you have done professional programming,
you often have in your runtime environment.
You have logging levels.
I don't know if you're familiar with that,
but you have debug level,
and you have info and warning and error,
and that's pretty standard in the logging frameworks.
If you call log debug and you construct this huge string, it will, Java will evaluate that
huge string.
Back then we couldn't splice, we didn't do string interpolation, we didn't have that
available in the language.
So all of our code was peppered with if log.is debug on and then it would call log.debug.
And that was a pain as a programmer to have to write that all the time.
So this thing is super easy and I often see in logging frameworks in Scala, I often see
call my name, because that way you don't evaluate this whole thing if you don't need it.
Also there's getorelse so if you have a none and you call getorelse, what getorelse looks
like is def get or else y. And I'm just going to use x there x. So we're in some sort of...
For both of these, we have option x. I think it's plus x, but I can't remember. We'll talk
about that another week. But get or else, so this one is going to return option x, but
get or else it's going to return whatever this option contains or whatever else we pass.
Oh, and to be consistent, I should also make it so that it's y.
Call my name because I may have this complex expression, compound expression here, and
I may not want to actually do all this work if I actually have a value.
Okay. So those are option types. Not too difficult, but we use these a lot more than we would
use null in scottler and in other languages like Haskell and functional programming all
around. Okay. So that's option types. And there's a worksheet on this. I put it here
for this week. You don't have to do it this week. It's really just set you up for the next homework
and the next quiz. But you can do it if you have time, but I would, again, focus on the midterm
study guide because that's your big thing to solve or to work on for this week.
Okay, now we'll talk about one of my favorite topics, tail recursion.
So I might say to an AI, in Scala-3 new syntax, implement a recursive function to compute the Fibonacci numbers.
And it will dutifully produce something like this, which matches the mathematical definition of Fibonacci.
So let's actually test this code out a bit.
Hopefully this compiles, I didn't test it.
Okay good, so if I say Fibonacci zero, I should get zero.
If I say one, I should get one.
If I say two, you should get one.
And if I say three, so you can see how this will go, I should get two and then so on,
So we'll do one more four.
Great.
Now if I say 54, it's going to hang, or eventually it'll give me a result.
This is actually a homework assignment in my data structures one material.
We do this in Java, and we find that we end up with this will in any way when you do this
in Java in the homework that I give the students there.
This takes like maybe an hour to run.
See how you're repeating yourself here?
Every single time you're always going to create this tree,
where you're always doing all this work over and over and over
and over and over again.
Does everybody see that?
So sometimes the mathematical definition of a function,
while it's great for us to look at and reason about,
isn't the most useful for efficiency when computing.
So this has 30 and 45.
I don't know if this is ever not doing exactly.
It's gonna just go on for a while.
So then you might tell the AI, make it fast.
This is not good.
I want it faster.
So it might come up with something like this.
So what's different here?
We have this extra parameter, right?
And what's this extra parameter?
It's a mutable NAP and we're keeping track of the results as we go.
So we get a result, we're going to store it in the map so
that if we ever need that number again, we don't have,
Fibonacci of whatever that number is again.
We don't have to recomput it all.
We don't have to repeat ourselves.
There's actually a principle in software engineering called dry,
don't repeat yourself.
So this technique is called memoization.
They talk about that often in algorithms.
So it's also called dynamic programming.
But here's a question.
So now what we've done is we've made this faster, but we have this map, and if we're
doing big number, 54, for example, or a hundred or a thousand, we're going to store every
single number for all time while this function executes, right?
So do we really need to keep all those numbers ever computed?
And so, the question you can ask is, does this truly solve the problem?
Well, so it might work and it might be more efficient in terms of run time.
But is it more efficient in terms of space?
That's the question that we ask.
So, does that truly solve the problem, or does it create a new problem?
So, now we're going to talk about how we get recursive iteration without stack penalty,
and without recomputing immediate results.
So, those are the two things we saw.
So, we will now identify and express something called tail recursion.
We talked about this a little bit before, but now we're going to make it nice and clear.
So if I have this function sum, I'm summing the elements of my list.
If my list is empty, I'm going to use 0, additive identity, right?
So the sum of an empty list is just 0, and if I have x followed by some...
x is my head, and that's an int, followed by some rest of my list, I'm going to recursively
compute the sum and add my x to it. So, this actually is the same as if we wanted
to do a fold left. You can do it this way. So, this is our combining function. This
is our zero element. So, this is what happens if I call sum with my list 112131.
So, this will expand, it will match the list that we get is going to be this case
here so it'll match here so it'll expand to this so it'll say 11 because that's
gonna bind to X plus some of the rest of the list so see what that looks like.
There. I had to go, I had to actually go one step further but it starts by calling
some of this and then it takes the 11 and converts it to 11 plus some of the
rest of the list. And then I will recursively do this for 21, 31, nil. And I'll get back.
And then I'll do this for 31, nil. And if I call sum on nil, this time I'm going to match that
first case at line 2 on the left. And so that'll turn into 0. And then we'll just roll up the recursion.
You'll end up with 63.
So here we're summing up the left to after the last recursive call returns.
What does this stack look like?
So, when we're doing this, if we think about the call stack.
So, when we call sum, I like to draw my stacks going up.
So we call sum.
And here we have a stack frame.
And out in memory somewhere on our heap, we have a list, 112131.
And so, sum is going to have an excess which is going to point to this.
And actually, let's make it super clear.
It's going to point to this whole thing, 11, 21, 30.
That's the list it's pointing to.
Okay.
So then when I match on that first case, I'm going to have,
this is actually not going to be a named variable.
Oh, actually, it is a named variable.
I'm sorry.
It's X, and X has 11, right?
Because we matched on that.
And we'll have Ys is going to point to this, the remainder of the list.
Everybody call that?
That's how that works.
I drew that kind of funny, right?
Like, I guess I should change, because I crossed my arrows.
Let's try fixing them.
So we have ys, xs.
And xs points to that, and ys points to that one.
That's a little better, a little easier to see.
And when we continue down the path here, we recursively call sum, so this time we're
We're gonna have XS is gonna point to the same thing here.
But YS is gonna point to...
Oh, I should be using the correct names, look at that.
Stop me if I use the wrong names.
It should be rest, because that's what we called it there, rest.
So this time, rest is gonna point to,
I'm gonna use a different color.
Rest is gonna point to 31,0.
Right, and x is gonna point to
is going to have 21.
So you see what we're doing here is,
as we make these recursive calls,
we're building these stack frames
and we're holding onto data in these stack frames.
So I could keep going, but I'm gonna stop there.
So the call stack has these activation records
for active calls.
That's why I call that a stack frame.
That's another term we use for it.
So an activation record is pushed when a function or method call is made.
So that's why when we recursively called, we added another stack frame.
And we pop when a function or method returns,
we're used to that, we learn that in systems.
Some run time environments will limit the size of our call stacks.
So this can cause problems.
So in Java it's gonna be dynamic but
when we run out of space,
we're gonna get a stack overflow error.
It's called a stack overflow because we used up
all the space in our memory for method calls.
See, in C we have something like where I think we set
some kind of a limit that we can set in the operating system.
And I don't know what the behavior is,
but my guess is if we exceed that,
we just crash, we'd probably try to touch memory
that the C program is not supposed to touch.
So now let's look at what happens if we change the code
to put the Z element here in the parameter list.
And we're now going to complete the running sum as we go,
and we'll see the behavior, how this changes.
So I'm going to start off with sum.
And we have xs, which is going to be our list.
And here we have the other variable we have is x.
Oh, and we also have z after I left off the z.
So we have, let's do the Z here, and then X, and then rest, I'll give you more space.
Rest.
So X, S is going to point to 11, 21, 31, nil.
and z is going to contain, when we first call it, we're going to pass 0.
Oh, maybe I should show you that.
Yes, we'll start with z equals 0.
That's the default.
So z is going to be 0.
x is going to have 11, and rest is going to point to,
I'll start using the colors because that'll make it clearer.
s is going to point to the rest of the list.
And now, if we call sum again,
we'll have the same variables.
We'll have xs, which will point to the same thing here.
z.
This time, z is going to get what?
It'll get wake.
I heard it, 11, right, because we took the original z, which was 0, from the lower- from
this one and added x to it.
So we take 0 plus 11, in that order, and we pass it here as the second parameter.
So that goes into z.
And then we have an X which is going to get 21 and we have a rest which this time will
point to this part of the list, 31 and 0.
So we'll keep going.
And we'll do this.
So if we follow how this proceeds, the computation proceeds, we're always adding that X element
as we call into the next level down.
So we'll end up with 63.
So what we can say now is that all of our recursive calls are in tail position.
So the way that I like to think about this is if you look at this and you see that the
last thing we do in any of the cases, either we're returning something outright or we're
calling ourselves recursively but we're not doing any work after the fact, then we can
say that all the recursive calls are in tail position.
So our result sum is actually computed before the recursive call is made.
And now the stack, we've illustrated how it's different.
But there's no work to be done when we come back.
We don't even need to hang on to this x anymore.
Now, if you don't declare it tail recursive, I think the compiler will actually eliminate
what it doesn't need.
So this is the tail recursive version, and we do this in data structures one.
Well, we do this for any kind of recursion.
But with tail recursion, we don't get this in Java.
in Scala, we can actually rewrite it this way. Isn't this the same as what we just had?
So this is the tail recursive version. But if we want to rewrite it to a loop, we can
do this, we can start using variables, bars. And then if we have nil, we just return the
z element, and otherwise, we say, oh z, we update z. So here we're using a bar, then
So you can do it that way.
And you can also do it this way.
So how is this different?
We have, oh, we're just reassigning xs to L.
And this is showing you how you can sort of think of this.
can think of it as a recursive mutable loop.
And then it's just evolving this as we go.
So instead of having our internal function have a parameter,
this is our nested function.
Instead of having that parameter, we're
kind of showing you how to get to a loop.
And then when we get over here, we
replace the matching with if-else,
And then this is like a classic loop
where we have our variables, our mutable variables,
and while a while loop.
We're used to that.
We've seen that before.
So what the compiler actually does is it sees that.
And it might actually give you a warning
and say you should declare this tail recursive.
And it creates the instructions that
are equivalent to this.
It can only do that if this is in tail call position.
So here's an exercise with Fibonacci.
So the time complexity of this is going to be big O of 2 to the N.
So I'm not going to develop that and prove that.
But if you think about how it's repeating itself over and over again,
repeating the work all the time,
it's going to take a really long time to execute.
So we want to know how to improve it.
So we could represent the sliding window in the arguments so this is one way to do it.
So you just keep track of the last two, right, and then you can go on down.
And now you can also use the lazy list which we've talked about last week.
So in this one, we have big int zero, big int one, and then we're calling fib.zip which
is mapping each element to the next element.
That's what this dot, zip, it's mapping to its tail, sorry, it's pairing each element
pairwise with the next element.
And this is a lazy list, so it can be infinite.
And then we're always going to map
and we're going to do this addition here.
So if I tell my AI, I want you to implement a tail recursive
function to compute Fibonacci numbers,
it might do something like this.
So if you use this tailrack annotation in your code, the compiler will complain if in
fact you are not tail recursive.
The compiler will allow you to write functions that are tail recursive...recursive functions
that are tail recursive that are not tail recursive, but you should strive to write
something that is tail recursive, and so if you are writing something and you see that
oh, look, I don't have anything and that's, that I have no work to do after I call my recursive function,
I can declare it tail recursive.
And then the compiler will check and make sure that it can actually optimize this whole thing to a loop.
So these specific instructions can help generate good code.
So there's something else called continuation passing.
So can all functions be made tail recursive?
So if I have this here, I have a tail recursive accumulator.
So here what I'm doing is I'm summing the elements of my list,
the beginner, my zero element is the int 0,
so when I get to null, I'm just going to take z.
If I have something other than an empty list then I'm going to add z and
my initial z is 0 to x.
So if I call that, I can add an extra argument for
a function to take the return value.
So let's see what that looks like.
So what I'm doing here is I have my sum function.
And here, c is my continuation.
So this is actually a function to update this mutable state.
So this is called a continuation.
That's why it's C.
So what I'm saying is, well, I'm going to start S at minus 1.
And when I get to nil, I'm going to say C of 0.
And that's going to, this here is super shortcut syntax
for take the argument I got and update S to contain that.
So that's why you see S equals whatever.
So I got the argument down to nothing.
But I said I'm going to change my s now to contain that value.
That's what that means.
So by doing this, what I'm doing is
I'm passing a function to update this mutable state.
So you can always do this.
So we don't really need it for this one.
But you can always do this continuation passing
to make something tower recursive.
So, compilers of functional languages will use this as an intermediate form, similar
to static single assignment in imperative languages.
So our summary, tail-call optimization avoids the performance penalty of creating activation
records.
So because the compiler can just optimize out all these recursive calls and turn it into
loop, I don't have to deal with the stack potentially growing to a point where I
get a stack overflow. And it's faster. It will actually end up overwriting... I
guess the compiler will probably overwrite an existing activation record,
meaning it overwrites the data in that activation record, just like you do in a
while loop iterative solution with mutable state. All of our recursive calls
have to be in tail position. That's the last operation we do. So when you saw like x plus
sum ys, this was not the last operation. Because the last operation is the plus. And you can
use continuation passing to replace the return value with a function that is called upon
return. So that just replaces the return value.
So if I want to rewrite this is just an example, if I want to take factorial
and rewrite it to a loop.
This is my tail recursive version. Here's my recursive version with mutable
state. This is using the same kind of progression
we used before for the Fibonacci example.
So now we've gone from this recursive function expression
of solving the problem to using this nested loop
that has a parameter on the function,
on the nested function.
And now what we've done is we've removed that.
We're moving, we're inching ever so,
ever so slightly toward the while loop.
And this is the loop with mutable data,
so this is the way we would have done that
iteratively in the available state.
And that is tail call optimization.
So tail recursion is a fun topic.
I enjoy.
OK.
So I'm kind of doing this.
Like a little buffet of different stuff tonight,
because all of these topics are going
lead into some of the later topics we're going to discuss, but we're kind of jumping around
a little bit, so next we're going to talk about static and dynamic types.
So, how should we support programmers and interpreting memory content correctly? And
how should we support programmers in applying operations correctly? So we'll talk about
What are types?
Why do we have types?
We'll talk about the effects of static
and dynamic type checking, and I guess that's it.
I thought there was a third cold point.
So, look at this code.
This is programming without types.
So, what's difficult about this?
Does that make sense, just looking at that?
Is that easy to read?
What's it doing?
Is it easy to tell?
Not really, right.
So in C, this is how you had to do things in C. You could also have more specific versions
of things where you pass struts around, but oftentimes in C libraries you have these void
pointers. So we can use types. So here, what we've done, is we've defined a type node,
and we've said, okay, we're going to call it getNext. This is our getNext, here we have
a void start. We have to cast it and do all this de-referencing. So here, it's a little
easier to read, right? So get next, I'm going to return the next value of my node. Sorry,
the next element, the next node after this node. So here, I'm going to allocate a node,
I'm going to set my value to 42, I'm going to set my next to null, and then I'm going to
call get next on n and get back the next node.
So Python will overcome missing static types.
I don't know Python.
But it will do things like this.
Here's here.
You're doing reduce using a function over an iterable.
And there's some initial value there.
I don't know Python.
I don't want to ever program without types.
I've been programming with types my whole life as a programmer.
So I don't do Python.
So you have to come up with lots of examples.
You have to write lots of unit tests
to test all of your edge cases.
So types will eliminate a whole class of bugs.
So in C, our types, all they really
do is tell the compiler how much space to allocate.
That's what happens in C. So this gives the compiler
information that it needs.
Originally, C did not do type checking at compile time.
That just tells it how much space to use.
I think some of the C compilers now do some type checking.
But I don't know to what extent.
So the types will, in many of the languages we use,
they actually determine valid operations.
Earlier we talked about in the Interim Study Guide,
we had some type checking, questions
where you had to figure out what the types were.
And there were cases where things didn't comply.
So I can print line and call 1-2 because I can do minus on ints,
but I can't really do minus on strings.
There's no minus strings.
So we should get an error for that.
Types also provide us with documentation and
tell us something about the code we're looking at.
So types can be enforced statically with the compiler.
We call this early.
This is early type enforcement.
We can also do it dynamically.
We store type with the object, or you can be in early versions of C where it'd be like
all.
If we have dynamically typed language,
then we're tracking the type with the object at runtime.
We call this late type enforcement.
They said early binding.
Usually we use early and late binding,
which is maybe not exactly that offense.
So early type enforcement versus the early type enforcement.
So late is at runtime, and early is
You can find a function that works in a second file.
So dynamic type checking resolves types
or detects a failure at runtime, because we're tracking
the types at runtime.
And our dynamic languages will resolve the types,
detect failures at runtime.
So scheme is going to be dynamic.
So you could put in code like this.
I don't read scheme.
It looks like we're defining a function that does 5 minus 0.
that looks like it's a prefix notation.
So then if I try to run my function,
I'll get an error at runtime.
Expected type number dot hello.
Why is it saying that?
Well, it's doing five minus, and trying
to subtract the string hello from that integer.
JavaScript is also dynamic.
So we'll do some of this later in this course.
This is fun.
So I can try to have this statement in JavaScript
where I say five minus hello and I'll get not a number.
This is why I love JavaScript.
I'm being facetious here.
I don't like JavaScript at all.
That will be accepted,
but the type will resolve to not a number.
So in Java and Scala, we have static type checking.
So here in Java, we have int A equals five,
string B equals hello.
And we can try to do this, and we should get compiler error.
And also in Scala, we would do it this way.
We have a val A which has five, a val B which has hello.
And print.
And in both cases, we're going to get
some kind of a compile time error.
So here it's saying, you have a binary operator minus,
you have A minus B.
You can't have an int and a string,
and subtract them.
Makes no sense.
We can make the error dynamic in Java and Scala by casting.
So in Java, we do this here.
We're trying to take B, which is a string,
first we cast it to an object, then we cast it to an int.
And then we print this out.
So here we took our b as instance of int,
and then the compiler says, oh, OK, well, if that worked
when you run it, then I can do the subtraction.
Sure, no problem.
But at runtime, we'll end up with a problem.
So the compiler will accept the code.
But dynamic checking at runtime will catch the invalid cast.
So you'll see this class cast exception.
You may have seen that in Java.
So when you try to cast something that at runtime
you can't cast it to, you're going
to get that kind of an error.
You can also convert any static error into a dynamic error
by doing this.
Casting will turn compile time errors into runtime errors.
In static languages, variables have types.
So in Java, our variable a has type int.
So assigning hello to this variable
will not pass the compiler.
In Scala, our var a has the type int, and same thing.
We can't assign any string to that variable.
The compiler doesn't really know what's
contained in your variables at runtime?
I mean, I guess it could if there's something that's
static and never changes.
I'm sorry, if it's something that, well, static
is the right way to say that, but if it assigns it
in the code, something literal, maybe, and it never changes.
But in general, compilers do not know what value is held
in your variables at compile time.
So type inference will infer the most precise type possible.
So that study guide question we looked at that had the string and the int mixed together
for that list, and it said well, it's either a list, it's a list of int or string, or I
can't remember what order it did, string or int, it doesn't matter.
inferred that was the most precise thing you could say about the type of those
things. So in dynamic languages by contrast our variables don't have types.
So in our in our scheme function here we define this our main program we define
main, we define a and we set a to contain five and then we update a to
contain this string hello and display it that'll work just fine JavaScript we
can do that as well so we have a bar a we set it equal to the integer 5 we
update a to now contain the string hello and then we log it and we get out hello
perfectly fine so this notion of type conservativeness static type checking
Scala is sometimes conservative.
So runtime code modification is harder,
and compiler optimizations are based on types.
So here it might actually optimize this to just refer to i.
It still has to take s as a parameter
to this method, the string parameter.
But it may never use it.
dynamic type checking is not conservative,
f is always going to return i.
Runtime code modification is often easy,
and there are no compiler optimizations based on types.
So here's our summary.
Static type checking happens at compile time.
Variables have types that are often inferred.
The benefits are compile time detection of errors,
no unit tests for types.
You don't have to worry about things being
potentially the wrong type
because the compiler won't let you compile the code
in the first place.
You automatically get documentation.
So Scala doesn't always require
that I include the type annotation on things,
but I often tell my IDE to add it
because it's very useful for others,
and for myself when I'm trying to reason about some code.
So you get documentation because the compiler
can figure out what the type is.
And so when you insert the type and know what it is,
faster runtime.
So at runtime, it doesn't have to worry
so much about what types things are.
So it doesn't have to look up the type.
It doesn't have to make any, do any work to do that part.
and it's going to end up consuming less memory at runtime.
Remember at runtime, we're just dealing with some kind of something something like
assembly language.
The Java virtual machine has its own assembly language essentially.
The JVN bytecodes are that, so it doesn't have to worry so much,
because if the compiler is doing all this enforcing at runtime,
you can just forget about it.
With dynamic typing, that's going to check at runtime.
Variables themselves don't have types,
the values have types, but the variables don't.
And the benefits are that this can be more flexible,
it can be conceptually simpler,
a lot of initial programming courses teach people
to use Python and it can be easier to reason about.
It compiles faster, if it does compile,
if it does compile, and then you can have easier runtime code generation and modification.
So back when I learned how to program in my first year of college, everybody was doing
C. So I had a natural progression from C to C++ to Java, and by the time I was a professional
software developer, I was working with Java. Not JavaScript, Java. And I was like, I want
compiler to tell me all of these things that I get wrong. I like that. That was intellectually
satisfying to me. So I've stayed away from all the dynamic languages. And there's been
plenty of money and working in back end software development. So static languages are often
used. They're more likely.
All right. And then our last topic, we have 20 minutes left, and we have 10 slides. That's
about my usual algorithms.
Our last topic is undefined behavior.
So what should happen if the language does not
specify the meaning of some construct?
So what should happen if, let's say, x is holding eight bits
and we have 7 is our value, and then we do x plus 1.
So if we want to actually visualize this.
Oh wait, should that be four bits?
So I'm going to do it with four bits.
So 7, if we think about how we would represent 7, these are positions we would have, 0, 1,
1, 1, right, so 1, 2, 4, so 4 plus 2 plus 1 gives us 7.
and we add one, and we end up with,
one, zero.
What does that mean?
Well, sometimes we represent the sign here,
in this bit.
This is, say, eight.
Eight bits, which is pretty standard.
But maybe this should change to like, whatever,
two to the seventh power, or two to the seventh power,
whatever that is, we can do an x plus one.
I should maybe think about that slide.
But that's what this is getting at.
What does that mean, right?
So let's talk about undefined behavior.
So, natural numbers are only partially useful as integer arithmetic semantics.
So remember earlier, we had this rule here.
So this is our num rule, right?
So if we have a number, n, that's just going to be itself, right?
we need to also remember that we're dealing with our computers that have memory expressed in terms
of how many bytes for use and how many bits are in those bytes and all of that so these are our
bounds so we're gonna have to add integer bounds so and is going to be and if we have a lower bound
is minus 2 to the 63rd power. So this is basically 20 bytes. I can't do math
tonight, but 63 bits and 63 bits 2 to the 63rd minus 1. So what do we do when we
have overflow? So if we have this example here that I did, this could be overflow.
you can consider this more to fall.
So we would have to have an error.
So this rule is saying, OK, if I have expression 1, e1,
evaluates to b1, and I have this variable store, e0,
that maybe gets modified while I'm doing that evaluation.
And then I have e2, and that takes my, did I call that e?
I meant to call that xi.
Xi zero, xi one, and again, it's like xi is the variable store.
So then I evaluate E1, I get V1.
I evaluate V2, I get V2.
I might be modifying the variable store as I go.
So this is saying if my V1 plus V2 is within the bounds, right?
These are the bounds, right?
So if I'm not within the bounds,
so this is saying if I'm not within the bounds,
that I'm going to have an error.
This is going to take this expression
and end up with an error and it may go through.
It's going to do all the evaluations,
so we're going to end up with Psi 2, and again.
So here's underflow and overflow.
So this is kind of interesting.
So I actually, when I first taught this,
I actually put this into the compiler and see what it does.
So this is doing different optimization levels, I think.
So if I do this code, what it's doing is it's just like,
well, I don't hit the minimum value.
So to determine if I'm at the minimum value,
it says x minus one greater than x.
If that's true, or if it's not min value,
it'll keep decrementing i.
So if I use this optimization level,
it will actually terminate and stop.
If however, and this is with GCC,
if I use this different optimization level,
I'll get an infinite loop.
Because it's doing extra checking
with that optimization level.
So here's our rule for sequential composition.
Remember if we have e1 followed by
that colon in our language, followed by an E2, and we're gonna evaluate each one of those
with our variable store there. Um, the resulting value here is gonna be V2, which is whatever
E2 evaluated to because we were processing these first and then the result value isn't
really used. And here we have our addition rule. So this is here just to sort of... I
was sort of reviewing the slides, why is that there? I think on the subsequent slides it
clearer why that's there but this is just our addition rule so we have
expression 1 plus expression 2 gives us v1 plus v2 and to get there we had to be
able to evaluate expression 1 to the value and evaluate expression 2 to
another value and again we have our variable store that may be modified as an example
so we chain the stores psi 0 is used in evaluating e1 and produces psi 1 psi 1
is used in evaluating e2 and it produces psi 2 and this is true for both the
sequential composition rule and the addition rule so what happens if we have
okay so keep that in mind what happens if we have an undefined order of
operations all right so we've got some code here let's look at these functions
So we have this global variable count.
We have an f that's going to increment count
and then return that value.
We have a g that's going to increment count
and then check to see if it's bigger than or equal to 2,
and then it's going to give us 5.
And if it's not bigger than or equal to 2,
it's going to give us 3.
And then we have our h, which is going to add the two arguments
together.
These are all h's here.
So if I have this code, I have, I'm calling h,
But before I call h, I have to call these two functions
to produce the values, right?
And the question is, well, what is the order of the execution?
Do we execute f first or do we execute g first?
We're used to Java and Scala.
And in Java and Scala, we would do this in order.
That's defined.
But in c, it actually isn't defined.
And then the other thing that's going on here
is that this business here, that's this line 15.
There's no, I think we might have covered this before,
but in C, you have to hit that comma operator
or a semicolon operator before you can do something like this
and have it be defined.
So what I'm doing here is I'm saying, well, why?
I'm adding one to y and updating y, and then I'm doubling y.
So depending on which one executes first, that could affect the outcome.
And in c, this is not defined.
So if you use clang, which is one of the compilers, you'll get this warning.
And here you're doing "-w all".
So give me all warnings.
And it says, well, here's a warning.
this is unsequenced
remember the sequence operator in C
is the comma
so this is unsequenced
now if you run this code out of Clang
you're going to get 6 and 20
you can actually
go and look and see
figure out how it got to 6
and how it got to 20
and we can do that but we're running out of time
so I'm not going to spend all the time
deep diving
but what it's essentially doing
is it's a different order of operations,
because the order of operations isn't defined.
So it's going to do A first.
I guess it's telling us, right?
So it's going to do F first,
and then put it into A,
and then B, and then put it into...
Sorry, and then G, and put it into B,
and then add those two things.
and then it's gonna do this,
which is, it's gonna do in this order,
it's gonna do this expression and then that expression.
And that will end up with the output
that we had there, six and 20.
The other one,
so I think this is the same code.
I actually tested this earlier, too.
This you put into GCC.
And you'll also get with this flag and this optimization level,
I guess.
I think that's what capital point means.
I haven't done professional SEAT and elements,
so I'm not sure.
But I think it's an optimization level.
I said that earlier, but I did qualify.
Yeah, so it could be doing this in a different order.
So what this code will do, it will actually execute G
first, which is over here.
So it's actually gonna execute the one on the right first.
And so this compiler does it differently
from the other compiler, right?
And so that is because
the language does not define the order.
And so it's up to the compiler how to interpret it.
So here we did g first, and we got our b.
We did f second, and we got our a,
and because there is dependency here,
they're sharing some memory,
the results can be different.
And then it's going to do the y equals y plus 1.
And then y equals y times y.
And then y equals y plus y.
Oh, that's the last one, right?
That's this final part here.
We'll do it in that order.
So you have a different order of operations.
So for undefined executions, the compiler can do whatever it wants.
We don't get this really in Java and Scala because they decided to define it.
But this can lead to some really surprising compiler optimization.
So you'll see different results.
There's something called C null pointer optimization one.
I clicked this earlier.
I was like, where is this taking me?
It's going to bring this up.
I think what this point of this one is, oh, yeah, I watched a video once that used this.
I think what the point of this is is that even though you never call this,
it's doing like some function aliasing or something.
And even though you never call it, so here you have,
even though you never call never call, so you never update do to get erase all,
which is going to erase, it's gonna like RM-RF your whole system,
which is gonna basically delete all your files on your disk, right?
That's what this is doing.
Don't ever do this, by the way, don't try this on your machine, okay?
because if you're using Linux especially, don't try this.
But what could happen is because the compiler could see
that the only time you ever do an assignment for do,
which is this alias, it's only here.
And it's never happening ever again.
And so what it'll do is it'll be like,
well, I'll assign do to contain whatever erase all it has.
And it doesn't understand English,
so it doesn't even know what you're trying to do.
but the compiler will do this thing and then in your main program when you run it,
it will actually execute erase all even though you never called, never called
because the compiler made a decision.
This is what's going on there and it's fraught with peril so be careful.
So here's our summary.
So undefined behavior will be resolved in the compiler
And the compiler will decide what is the meaning of undefined programs.
And actually, there's some videos out there with Professor Riley.
And he says, it's not C if it's undefined.
Because you can't look at it and you can't say definitively what the program does.
Because it's undefined.
This can actually present security risks in your code.
There's lots of examples that you can go check out.
So here's some more examples.
I didn't really look at them.
there's your Wikipedia article,
gratuitous Wikipedia article, and then
here's a guide to, somebody's blog,
a guide to undefined behavior in C and C++.
So, yeah, you can read about that.
So the reason why a lot of this stuff is undefined is back when C was being
developed,
they didn't want to impose this on the compiler,
like a decision on the compiler that was why they did that
but it ended up being really problematic so that's why when Java
Scala and other languages come along they actually define this stuff
so formal semantics can be analyzed for contradictions and
completeness so sometimes if there is something that's
undefined in if something is not
it could escape the designers of the language that something was undefined
defined and they've done formal proofs.
They actually had to go back and do formal proofs about Java
and then correct the language to correct
the semantics of the language so that they've removed
undefined behavior.
Because there's one Java compiler.
It was originally created by Sun and now it's owned by Oracle.
So there's one.
Well, there's different Java compilers,
but there's a Java language specification
which tells you what things mean.
And that is it, so we're at the end.
And that's all of our stuff for tonight,
so we got through it all, which is great.
I added something later on, week after the midterm.
I've never done this before,
but I want to give a little presentation
on how Russ deals with memory safety.
So we'll talk about memory safety
after, the week after the midterm,
And I'll give you a taste of Rust,
so you can kind of see what's going on,
how Rust solves some problems that we'll talk about
much, much later.
So I'm kind of excited about that,
because I'm learning Rust right now.
I'm a language geek, so my company is like,
we're going to leave Scala, and we're going to go to Rustland.
They're going to do ProLang.
So I wanted to kind of share what I'm learning with you all.
So we'll get to that.
But for the midterm, just weeks one through four,
So formal semantics is the endpoint
for studying for next week.
These are here.
Well, this is the lecture notes,
but the worksheets are here for you.
If you have time, do them.
If not, prepare to double up before you do next week.
I don't know how long these are taking.
How long are the worksheets taking?
Are they taking half an hour, 45 minutes, an hour?
Longer?
What do you think we're talking about?
An hour?
So hopefully they're useful.
but I'll try not to add any more.
I usually do no more than two in a week.
So the thing is, we're running up against the midterms,
so if you have time, do them.
And if not, it's okay to wait
until after you've taken the exam.
All right, great.
Any questions about the exam or next week,
the next couple of weeks.
I'll send the details of the plan,
for the schedule and where we're meeting and when,
office hours changing and all that.
So great.
Thanks for your attention and have a good night.
Did the compiler finish the.
Oh, the 54, the Fibonacci.
It did finally.
I don't know how long it took because I didn't time that.
It took a while.
I'm sure because we saw it.
If I had changed that to the loop implementation,
I would be like done.
Because it's just updating memory.
It's not repeatedly trying to recompute the same things over and over again,
unaware of what it's already done.
Try it out on your own.
Jayden, are you still there?
Yes.
Well, next week is the midterm,
so you can probably plan to join around 7.30, 7.35.
Awesome. Sounds good. See you then.
All right. See you then.
Now, I'm going to get into it.
I think I'll make it really easy.
I can't tell you that I'm going to make it really easy to make it easy.
I do not want to make it easy.
I think I'll make it easy.
I want to cut the raw cut from the pan.
You can cut the raw cut from the pan.
Now I'll have to use the same size to do this.
All right.
I'll use the first coat of the purple.
The color of the pink is a little gray, but the color of the purple is not too good.
I use the color of the purple.
I use the color of the pink which is the purple.
so
10,000
1,000
11,000
So, let's get into it.
.
Thank you.
all right
And now I just wait to see it, that's how we did it.
How did you do this?
Okay, so that's all good.
Thank you.
Yeah I say I got like
This actually takes time to upload them.
True, true, true.
Now.
Thank you.
...
All right, so I'm going to do that now.
Thank you.
.
I'll show you in the next episode.
Thank you.
.